<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present state and condition of Ireland, but more especially the province of Ulster humbly represented to the kingdom of England / by Edmund Murphy, Secular priest and titular chanter of Armach, and one of the first discoverers of the Irish Plot.</title>
            <author>Murphy, Edmund, Secular priest.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10136</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13111681</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13111681</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97682</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51623)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97682)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 746:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present state and condition of Ireland, but more especially the province of Ulster humbly represented to the kingdom of England / by Edmund Murphy, Secular priest and titular chanter of Armach, and one of the first discoverers of the Irish Plot.</title>
                  <author>Murphy, Edmund, Secular priest.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Boulter ..., and Benj. Alsop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Ulster (Northern Ireland and Ireland)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:97682:1"/>
            <p>I Do Appoint ROBERT BOUL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER and BENJAMIN ALSOP to Print this my Narrative, Entituled, The Preſent State and Condition of IRELAND, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>January</hi> 17. 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Edmund Murphy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97682:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Preſent State AND CONDITION OF IRELAND, But more eſpecially the PROVINCE OF ULSTER, Humbly repreſented to the KINGDOM OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>BY EDMUND MURPHY, Secular Prieſt, and Titular Chanter of ARMACH, and one of the Firſt Diſcoverers of the IRISH PLOT.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for R. Boulter at the Turks Head in Cornhil, and Benj. Alſop at the Angel and Bible in the Poultrey. 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97682:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97682:2"/>
            <head>THE Preſent State AND CONDITION OF IRELAND, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe Firſt occaſion of Diſcovering the Plot carried on by Dr. <hi>Oliver Plunckett,</hi> and other Treaſons, was a difference that aroſe between Mr. <hi>John Dermond</hi> of <hi>Caſtletown-Bedlow</hi> in the County of <hi>Louth,</hi> and one Enſign <hi>John Smith,</hi> as the Reader will underſtand in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of the following Relation.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>The Informant being Pariſh Prieſt of <hi>Killevey</hi> and Chantor of <hi>Armach,</hi> at which time the inhabitants of the ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſuffered great dammage and loſſes by the Tyranny of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97682:3"/>
one <hi>Redmond Hanlon</hi> and his Confederates; the ſaid <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> being a cruel Murderer, Rebel and Tory, (which is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the whole Kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi>) againſt whom the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant preached in open Aſſembly, and not only againſt his Aſſociates, but alſo againſt all ſuch as relieved and harbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſaid <hi>Redmond;</hi> which he the ſaid <hi>Redmond</hi> hearing, ſent many Threats to the Informant, willing him to deſiſt his reflections againſt him and his Companions, or otherwiſe the effect of the ſaid Informants preaching ſhould prove bitter to him elf in the latter end: for they proteſted to make him tread the ſame ſteps with ſorrow back again to other Kingdomes, whence he came, upon default of not taking the Advice afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> perceiving the Threatning ſent to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant could not anſwer the end thereof, made an Edict throughout that Barony, (therein declaring) that whoever came to hear the ſaid Informant, ſhould for the firſt time pay one Cow, and for the ſecond Miſdememeanor of that kind ſhould pay two Cows, and for the third his life; which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly he executed; having taken one Cow from <hi>John M. Fulloney,</hi> proceeded to take the ſecond; and in purſuance of one of the Informants Pariſhioners (out of his own houſe) by name <hi>Cully Mackavell,</hi> barbarouſly murthered him; by which the Informant ſaw into what danger he had brought himſelf and others by his Preaching, therefore hired a Curate to offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate in his ſaid Pariſh, and himſelf ſeldom or ever after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted thither.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>It followed that one <hi>Cormacke Raver O-Murphy,</hi> Herdſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to one Lieutenant <hi>Henry Baker,</hi> committed ſeveral Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries againſt ſeveral perſons of the County of <hi>Louth</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach,</hi> being encouraged thereunto from the conſideration he had of his Maſters being an Officer of his Majeſties ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Army, and concluding it ſafeguard enough to colour his Roguery, which ſo emboldened him to that height of inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, that his Maſter could not be ſuppoſed able to anſwer to the one third of his Villany, upon which he was neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to deſert the ſervice of his ſaid Maſter: which done, he joyned himſelf to the Tories <hi>(viz.)</hi> the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> and his company: leaving <hi>William Murphy</hi> his Brother as a pledge to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97682:3"/>
ſerve his ſaid Maſter, Lieutenant <hi>Baker:</hi> his Unkle <hi>Bryan Murphy</hi> then ſerving Enſign <hi>John Smith,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> by his notorious actions rendered all of his name obnoxious though never ſo honeſt: ſo that it was concluded upon by ſuch to joyn iſſue together to bring him back dead or alive; and the firſt opportunity they found for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was about <hi>September</hi> 1678; the Informant being at a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his ſaid Pariſh on <hi>Sunday;</hi> and after ſervice demanded of one <hi>Thomas Murphy</hi> who had been abſent, what kept him ſo long; the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> in his Reply, called aſide the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant with others of the chief of the ſaid Pariſh, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed them that the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> with ſeven more, were drinking in a certain place called <hi>Carick Stickin,</hi> about a mile diſtant from the reſidence of the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> and <hi>Smith;</hi> wherefore the Informant called others of his Pariſh (that were graver than the reſt) to conſult what was beſt to be done in this matter, to which ſome of them replyed, that they durſt not give notice to the Kings Officers, leſt they might be diſappointed; adding further, that when ever the ſaid Rebels had intelligence of the Informers, they would come and burn their Houſes ſoon after; but the Informant apprehending the ſlaviſh fear they were poſſeſſed with, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired immediately to the ſaid Lieutenant <hi>Baker</hi>'s houſe, without any further Conference, ſending a Letter by one <hi>Art O Quine,</hi> unto the ſaid Lieutenant <hi>Baker,</hi> to meet the Informant in an Acre of ground near the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi>'s houſe; where he accordingly came, accompanied with his Wife; where the Deponent declared his buſineſs, acquainting the ſaid <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> that hard by his houſe were a company of Tories drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhewing him how the poor Countrey ſuſtained much dammage by them, and that now there was an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to take ſo many of them, if he would employ his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers thereabout. The ſaid Lieutenant replyed, that if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent would be bound that the Tories would abide his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, he would ſend for his Souldiers; to which the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent anſwered, he could not dive into their thoughts, but if the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> was loth to execute his Office, he would go himſelf, if he might be fitted with Arms, and help ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and take them. But the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> made this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that they did to the neighbourhood no dammage, and that <hi>Cormacke Raver O-Murphy</hi> was there, who he was ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Informant would not conſent to have ſlain among the reſt, ſeeing the Deponent and he were both of a name; but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97682:4"/>
the Informant proteſted the contrary: upon which the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> made him ſome ſlight promiſes to have them ſecured; and in hopes of the performance of what he had promiſed, the Informant departed, informing his Friends what had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed between him and the ſaid <hi>Baker;</hi> (all which proved of no effect) Notwithſtanding the Informant can depoſite upon Oath that the ſaid Rebels remained in the ſame Town all night drinking, at the houſe of one <hi>Richard Baths,</hi> and in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were ſo drunk that their Wenches were forced to help them away, ſo that if five or ſix Countrey-men had attempted to take them with the uſe of their Clubs, they might have eaſily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed the enterprize, notwithſtanding their Fire-Arms and Weapons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>That after the ſaid Lieutenant <hi>Baker</hi> received intelligence that a certain Tory, by name <hi>Art Mackardle,</hi> was in one <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund O Quin</hi>'s houſe, the ſaid <hi>O-Quin</hi> being Tenant to the Informants Father; and the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> and ſome of his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers lying in ambuſh till morning about the ſaid houſe; from whence then came forth the ſaid Tory, whom the Souldiers purſued from the Mountain to the Plain, where the ſaid Tory made his eſcape; at which the Souldiers ſeemed much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned and angry: in which rage they took Priſoners both men and women that they met with, under pretence of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the ſaid Tory in his flight, and that he had given his Arms (as he eſcaped) to ſome women; among the reſt the Informants nurſe was taken, and brought Priſoner to the Town of <hi>Dundalk:</hi> the day following being <hi>Sunday,</hi> a certain Boy came and informed the Deponent, that his Nurſe was taken by Lieutenant <hi>Baker</hi> and his Souldiers, under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence aforeſaid; the ſaid Boy affirming further, that he the ſaid <hi>Mackardle</hi> with two more of his Companions, were drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at one <hi>Richard Bath</hi>'s houſe, not far diſtant from the ſaid Enſign <hi>John Smith</hi>'s houſe, where the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> had been himſelf an hour before. The Informant ſending the ſaid B y to ſee whether the ſaid Tories tarried ſtill in the ſaid place, the Boy returned with the Affirmative, and how they had taken ſome Gentlemen as they paſſed by; at which anſwer the Informant haſted (in ſome fury) to the ſaid <hi>Baker;</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring what knavery was carried on between his Souldiers and Tories, and why the Informants Nurſe ſhould be detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Priſoner about the eſcape of <hi>Mackardle?</hi> ſeeing he was all day drinking near the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi>'s houſe: After which the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> promiſed her liberty, which he accordingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97682:4"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>That the Deponent having a Brother, by name <hi>Phele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Murphy,</hi> who travelling to <hi>Dundalk,</hi> paſſed by near to the ſaid Enſign <hi>John Smith</hi>'s houſe, in a certain hollow place where Sand and Gravel was before digged up, and who did he there meet but the ſaid <hi>Baker,</hi> and the foreſaid <hi>Cormucke Raver O-Murphy,</hi> a Rebel and proclaimed Tory, with others drinking hot waters and other Liquors; the ſaid <hi>Phelemy</hi> was ſomewhat aſtonied at firſt ſight hereof, but the leſs daunted at the ſight of the ſaid <hi>Baker;</hi> who commanded the ſaid <hi>Phelemy</hi> to light off his horſe, and take the Bible Oath not to reveal the meeting of the ſaid Tory and himſelf, (who were exerciſing themſelves in wreſtling) who preſſed ſo much drink on the ſaid <hi>Phelemy,</hi> that he was altogether uncapable to go about his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs any further, (nor return home) therefore ſtayed all night in the Field: in the mean time his horſe went home without him, where his friends immediately concluded he was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſlain or drown'd. And at this time <hi>William Murphy</hi> was Herdſman to the ſaid <hi>Baker,</hi> in the room of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſaid <hi>Cormucke,</hi> who was turned Rebel and Tory: though 'tis the Informants opinion, that had they all three been ſhaken together in a Bag, it would puzzle the underſtanding of a wiſe man to paſs an impartial judgement who was moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel and Tory of all the three; whether <hi>Cormucke,</hi> or his ſaid Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>William,</hi> or the Lieutenant himſelf: for the ſaid <hi>William Murphy,</hi> who was the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi>'s Herdſman (as before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) told the Deponent and ſeveral others, that he was as a faithful Meſſenger employed by the ſaid Lieutenant <hi>Baker,</hi> to carry Powder and Ammunition from his Maſter, for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of the Tories.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>That the Deponent was credibly informed by <hi>Katherine Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardle</hi> and ſeveral others, that the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> was God-father to the Child of <hi>Bryan Micardle,</hi> a proclaimed Tory: and the Informant had all other circumſtances relating to the ſaid Chriſtening told him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97682:5"/>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>That <hi>Richard Bath</hi> who lived the ſame year in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formants Pariſh (did and) can teſtifie that what was reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> in ſecret, in order to apprehend the Tories that frequented the ſaid <hi>Bath</hi>'s houſe; that it was no ſooner revealed, but the Tories were made acquainted therewith, repeating <hi>Verbatim</hi> what was delivered as matter of Secreſie to the ſaid Lieutenant <hi>Baker,</hi> relating to the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the ſaid Tories; which being underſtood by them, and that the ſaid <hi>Bath</hi> went about to betray them; the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> coming to his houſe, deſigned to kill him, but the Piece miſſing Fire, he made his eſcape: it was agreed on by the Tories to have him hanged at his own door; but giving him the liberty of taking the Oath, he ſolemnly ſwore on the Bible never to attempt the betraying them any more, by which means he was then ſpared. This was declared to the Informant and Mr. <hi>William Hethrington,</hi> by the whole fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the ſaid <hi>Bath,</hi> which afterwards was related to the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> by the Informant: With many more of the like tranſactions in the Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>That the ſaid <hi>Cormucke Raver O-Murphy</hi> growing very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, at length he forſook the great Rebel <hi>Redmond Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon;</hi> and by reaſon of his dexterity in plundering and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laging, he became the Ring-leader of a company diſtinct to himſelf; and at a certain time came accompanied with two of his men, to the Informants Pariſh <hi>(viz.) Killevey,</hi> and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered three Scotch-men there reſident, (the names of which were given to the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> by the Informant,) theſe three men being before Tributaries to the ſaid <hi>Redmond Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> it being become a cuſtome for the Countrey people of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to pay a certain ſum of money to the Tories for a Paſs to go unmoleſted (about their neceſſary affairs) from the reſt of the Gang: the ſaid three men complaining to the ſaid <hi>Redmond</hi> how they had been ſpoiled by the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, notwithſtanding their paying for Paſs and Protection from ſuch invaſion; the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> deſired them to have patience, and to colour the matter till ſuch time as he could take the ſaid <hi>Cormucke.</hi> Whereupon the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> repaired towards the place where he knew the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> was, and ſent to deſire his company to go along with the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> (as he pretended) to take a booty; which the ſaid <hi>Cormucke,</hi> not in the leaſt doubting, came accordingly to meet <hi>Hanlon,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97682:5"/>
having no more in company but two of his men, that had been at the taking of the fore-mentioned booty: but he no ſooner appeared before the ſaid <hi>Hanlon,</hi> but he was taken; which the two men perceiving their Captain in cuſtody, betook them to their heels, and one of them had made his eſcape, had not one <hi>Laghbin Hanlon,</hi> brother to the ſaid <hi>Redmond,</hi> taken a horſe from the Plow and purſued him, ſo that he was alſo taken: and all three <hi>(viz.)</hi> the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> and two men were guarded by fourteen Tories through the Informants Pariſh to one <hi>Neale Brolly</hi>'s houſe, where the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> ſent for the perſons that were robbed, and delivered them the ſaid <hi>Murphy,</hi> ſetting his two men at liberty, upon condition they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the goods aforeſaid, and withal writ a <hi>Mittimus</hi> to the next Juſtice of the Peace, with the ſaid <hi>Cormucke Murphy;</hi> who ſeeing himſelf liable to the cenſure of the Law, contracted with the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi>'s brother (before-mentioned) to give him 20 <hi>l.</hi> the week following to have his liberty, which he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; but without any Arms or Weapons: This being done in the face of the Informants Pariſh. The ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> being ſet at liberty, provided himſelf new Arms; ſends a Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to the ſaid <hi>Redmond:</hi> who refuſed to appear, but made ſolemn proteſtations to be revenged of the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick or private.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>The Informant receiving intelligence that one of his Horſes were ſtolen, obtains a warrant from Sir <hi>Hans Hamilton</hi> for the apprehending ſuch perſon or perſons in whoſe cuſtody the ſaid Horſe ſhould be found; which he effected accordingly: and brought the perſons before one Sir <hi>Toby Points,</hi> one of his Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace; where the Informant met one Captain <hi>William Butler,</hi> who enquired of the Informant if he had ſeen the great Rebel <hi>Hanlon</hi> lately. to which the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant replyed, he might eaſily be ſeen in the Informants Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, if there were any to look after him: Upon which the ſaid Captain called the Informant aſide, asking him if he could aſſiſt him with his advice how the ſaid Rebel <hi>Hanlon</hi> might be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended or kill'd: to which the Deponent anſwered, how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous it was to truſt the military men of that Kingdome; and withal related to the ſaid Captain how Lieutenant <hi>Baker</hi> had ſerved him in that matter; adding, that if any diligent and faithful Souldiers had taken the cauſe in hand, the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> had not tyrannized over poor people for two years laſt paſt: to which the ſaid Captain anſwered, if that ſervice was but once accompliſhed, the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> ſhould be disbanded: the ſaid Captain deſiring the Informants advice herein, they made a ſolemn Covenant among themſelves to be true to each other
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97682:6"/>
in the management of this affair: the Informant telling the ſaid Captain, that <hi>Cormucke Raver O-Murphy</hi> who had lately fallen out with the ſaid <hi>Hanlon,</hi> and being by him taken, he would prove the only man inſtrumental in this buſineſs: and withal, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant told the Captain he would by one means or other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> to this ſervice, if the ſaid Captain thought no danger would enſue thereon: hereupon the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain approved highly of the deſign, and deſired the Informant to promiſe the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> twenty Guineas and his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; and that he might have free regreſs to the ſaid Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſeeing he was hitherto no Murtherer, though a Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and Rebel: all which the Captain deſired to be done in his name.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>That the Informant made diligent ſearch and enquiry after the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> ſeveral days, and when he had found him, he privately declared to him what ſervice he was to do, with Captain <hi>Butler</hi>'s propoſitions for the performance of the ſame: withal the Informant told him, he would give him five pounds of his own over and above.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>That the Informant having delivered the meſſage, the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> made the following Objections, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that there was great difficulty that attended the accompliſhment of the ſaid deſign, by reaſon of the mutual correſpondency that was held between him and ſeveral of the Officers of the Kings Army, as alſo his intimacy with many of the Romiſh Clergy, though he the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> confeſſed he knew no Company leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned than the ſaid Captain <hi>Butler</hi>'s, by reaſon they were newly come to the Countrey, though five therein held corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency with the ſaid <hi>Hanlon;</hi> who by his Letters received daily encouragement that in a ſhort time he ſhould ſee war: and it was that expectation which obſtructed his departing the Kingdome before that time; nevertheleſs he the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> would work a device to have him deſtroyed or taken, with the aſſiſtance of Captain <hi>Butler</hi> aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>That the device ſhould be carried on thus: that the ſaid Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſhould ſend <hi>Cormucke</hi> a private protection, and twelve
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97682:6"/>
Souldiers, habited like the Tories; and this to be done in the night time; and that he would place ten of the ſaid twelve in Ambuſhment near the place where <hi>Redmond</hi>'s goods were ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to be, by him the ſaid <hi>Cormucke;</hi> and that himſelf would go with the other two, to a place where they might be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by the ſaid <hi>Redmond</hi> and his company, as ſuch as came to plunder; which when by them obſerved, they would make a retreat to bring the ſaid <hi>Redmond</hi> and company to the men in Ambuſh, who might preſently iſſue forth and take <hi>Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond:</hi> this the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> concluded to be the beſt courſe; to which the Informant gave his approbation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <p>That the Informant might not be ſuſpected by the ſaid <hi>Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi>'s friends living in his Pariſh, he concluded to go on foot to the ſaid Captain <hi>Butler</hi>'s houſe, which was ſixteen miles diſtant from the Informants habitation, it being alſo very tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous weather, he notwithſtanding repaired thither; and not finding the Captain at home, determined to ſend the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of his meſſage to <hi>Cormucke,</hi> and <hi>Cormucke</hi>'s anſwer, in a Letter by the hand of one of his Souldiers to the ſaid Captain <hi>Butler;</hi> by reaſon the Informant underſtood he was not to return in four days: and obtaining leave from his Lady for one of the Souldiers to go, he ſent the Letter accordingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>That the Informant ſuddenly after this, met the ſaid <hi>Cormucke,</hi> who demanded where his private Protection was, to which the Informant made anſwer, that he had not ſeen the Captain ſince, but that he had ſent him a relation of their Conference by one of his own Souldiers in a Letter; but the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> replied, he would neither truſt the Deponent nor the ſaid Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: for he further ſaid, that if the Souldiers came to execute the ſaid deſign againſt <hi>Hanlon,</hi> he would not ſtir without a Protection; for thereby himſelf was liable to be taken, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if what he intended could not be effected againſt the ſaid <hi>Redmond:</hi> upon the hearing of this matter, the Informant ſends a Meſſenger with a Letter to the ſaid Captain, therein ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting him with the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi>'s readineſs to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice aforeſaid: as alſo how he doubted the Informant's and ſaid Captains fidelity, ſeeing no Protection was provided for him: wherefore the ſaid Captain returned anſwer to the Deponent, that he had encloſed him a Letter in the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi>'s, from whom he expected a Protection ſhould be had the <hi>Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97682:7"/>
following; deſiring alſo the Informant to give the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> all the encouragement poſſible; aſſuring by Oath in his Letter, he would not for a Million of money any Trick ſhould be put on the ſaid <hi>Cormucke;</hi> but on the contrary, he ſhould have all reaſonable ſecurity for the performance of what was promiſed; which Letter the Informant ſent to the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> for his aſſurance of a Pardon and Protection, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter encouragement to proſecute his deſign.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p>That the firſt opportunity the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> took to expedite his intent was the ſurprizal of one <hi>David Molligan</hi> of the Town of <hi>Lecorry,</hi> in the County of <hi>Armach;</hi> who coming from <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> was commanded to ſtand (by the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi>) and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his Purſe; inſtead of which the ſaid <hi>David</hi> produced his Paſs under the great Rebel <hi>Hanlon</hi>'s hand, telling him, that his Father and <hi>Hanlon</hi> were Goſſips, and that the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> had often been ſheltered in his Fathers houſe when narrow ſearch was made by virtue of Sir <hi>Hans Hamilton</hi>'s Warrant for him: hereby the ſaid <hi>Cormucks</hi> had the opportunity to exaſperate the ſaid <hi>Hanlon,</hi> ſeeing his name and authority were made uſe of, for the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> on ſet purpoſe reſolved to contemn the ſame acquainting further the ſaid <hi>David,</hi> notwithſtanding his great eſteem of <hi>Hanlon,</hi> that he would not ſave the leaſt ſcrip of his goods for his ſake, till ſuch time the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> did reſtore the ſaid <hi>Cormuck</hi>'s Arms, which he had a little before deceitfully taken from him: hereupon the ſaid <hi>David</hi> promiſed he ſhould have them, provided he would reſtore his goods at the reception thereof, at a certain place appointed; which both parties agreed to.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>That the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> found out the Informant that night, and told him how opportunely, he had met with the great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel <hi>Hanlon</hi>'s Friend, and of the other circumſtances relating to the ſaid meeting by them appointed: but the Informant coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> not to ſend for the Souldiers aſſigned for that purpoſe, till he might be aſſured of <hi>Hanlon</hi> himſelf being at the place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97682:7"/>
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <p>That on the appointed day the ſaid <hi>David</hi> came to the place agreed on, placing the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> and his Aſſociates near thereunto; but providently one <hi>John Mackeevir</hi> going by, was by the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> and his company eſpied out of the Ambuſh, who immediately ſurprized him, and thought to have killed him, concluding it was the ſaid <hi>Cormucke;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This being in the night time.</note> but he cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out aloud for mercy, and the Rebels underſtanding by the voice that they were miſtaken, releaſed him; by this outcry the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> was alarmed that the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> and his company lay wait for him, therefore he abſented himſelf for that time: the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> thus miſſing his expectation, ſends the ſaid <hi>David Molligan</hi> and his Father-in-law to <hi>Patrick Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi>'s houſe, brother to the ſaid <hi>Cormucke;</hi> who lived about half a mile from the ſaid appointed place of meeting. The ſaid <hi>David</hi> and his Father-in-law <hi>Gibſon,</hi> made diligent ſearch for the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> there, where he was not found; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they returned with an anſwer to the ſaid <hi>Hanlon:</hi> who in great rage went to the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Patricke,</hi> and openly before all the Town cauſed him to be brought from the Plough, before the ſaid <hi>Hanlon,</hi> to be examined whether it was with his conſent the Traytor his Brother had robbed his Friend the ſaid <hi>David;</hi> to which the ſaid <hi>Patrick Murphy</hi> anſwered the Negative, declaring that he knew nothing of his Robberies: but notwithſtanding <hi>Hanlon</hi> proceeded to judgement, which was, that <hi>Patrick</hi>'s goods (if that might ſuffice) ſhould be reſponſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the robbery (taken by his Brother from the ſaid <hi>David</hi>) if not, his life: to which the ſaid <hi>Patrick</hi> replied, that he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his friends ſhould not be reſponſible for all his villanies, if ſo, they had enough to do; which the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> not able to bear, gave the ſaid <hi>Patrick;</hi> blow, and with an Oath affirmed, he ſhould dearly pay for the ſaid goods if they were not ſuddenly reſtored.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <p>That ſeveral meſſages paſſed between the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> and <hi>Cormucke;</hi> and at length determined among themſelves, that the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> ſhould reſtore his goods to the ſaid <hi>David,</hi> and that the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> would reſtore him his Arms; for which a time and place was appointed: which was no ſooner done, but the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> acquaints the Informant of the whole; deſiring him to inform Captain <hi>Butler</hi> therewith, and that the Souldiers might he placed in a readineſs near the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97682:8"/>
place, and the time aforeſaid: withal, that the Informant ſhould provide ſome Brandy and Hot Waters, which might be placed near the ſaid place, that <hi>Redmond</hi> and his Aſſociates might be decoy'd therewith: which the Informant at his own charge bought and diſpoſed of accordingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <p>That Fortune ſeemed to frown at this Enterprize; for it was eſtabliſhed by an Act, that the Tories relations ſhould make good what was taken from any; therefore the ſaid <hi>David Molligan</hi> got a party of Souldiers, who apprehended the ſaid <hi>Patrick Murphy,</hi> brother to the ſaid <hi>Cormucke;</hi> who told the Souldiers how the ſaid <hi>David</hi> and his Father-in-law came with the ſaid <hi>Redmond,</hi> threatning to kill him for the ſaid goods; that therefore he had employed his Wife to learn where the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> had diſpoſed of the fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned goods, which after ſhe found hid in a mountain; and at her return found her Husband apprehended by Souldiers; which Souldiers ſhe guided to the place where the goods were: upon which her husband was ſet at liberty: and the ſaid <hi>Redmond</hi> hearing thereof, was very much pleaſed thereat; and ſent word to the ſaid <hi>Cormucke,</hi> that he would neither meet him at the place appointed, nor reſtore him his Arms; which the ſaid <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mucke</hi> underſtanding, was very much enraged with his ſaid Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Wife. All which was declared to the ſaid Deponent from <hi>Cormucke,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Patrick</hi> his Brother.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <p>That after this the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> took the firſt opportunity he found to bring about his intention, and that was by rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing a certain Couſin of the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi>'s, who had a Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from him, and his name was <hi>Raverty;</hi> who one evening going from <hi>Dublin,</hi> told ſome Travellers, that were of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, that if they thought good he would preſerve them from any robbery if they would deliver their charge to him; for he told them he was a kinſman of ſome of the chief Rebels in the Kingdome, to which they conſented: but <hi>Cormucke</hi> no ſooner met them, but he made it a good argument to rob the ſaid <hi>Raverty,</hi> when he heard him mention the ſaid <hi>Hanlon;</hi> which done, he immediately repairs to the Informant, to deſire him to acquaint Captain <hi>Butler,</hi> that he had done ſomething to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the great Rebel, and that he knew he and his company would preſently be at his heels, and therefore deſired the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97682:8"/>
might be ready: which the Deponent hearing, went to <hi>Tondegree</hi> to ſee for the ſaid Captain, and there heard that the ſaid Captain was departed thence two days before, by the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi>'s Order, with his Company, a jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of fifty miles diſtant: to which the Deponent knew not what to ſay.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <p>That at this juncture of time was great ſtir in the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mants Pariſh and other places near adjacent, narrow ſearch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there made by the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> and his Confederates, for the ſaid <hi>Cormucke:</hi> upon this account ſeveral were apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Hanlon,</hi> as being in Confederacy with <hi>Cormucke;</hi> among the reſt was taken one <hi>Bryan O-Hagby</hi> and <hi>John Hamilton,</hi> for revealing that ſome of the Kings Souldiers were lookers on when the Tories apprehended them; and did never attempt to impede thoſe things acted by the Tories ſo openly, in the ſight of all reſident in thoſe parts; who dared not to make the leaſt oppoſition, being as much afraid of the Souldiers as Tories.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <p>That within two nights following the Informant arrived at home from <hi>Tondegree,</hi> at whoſe return the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> came to him, and enquired for the Souldiers he was to have for the effecting his deſign; telling the Informant he was well ſatisfied where the ſaid <hi>Redmond</hi> lay: adding how he and his Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates had been in the purſuit of him the ſaid <hi>Cormucke,</hi> ſince the Informant had been abſent: to all which the ſaid Informant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, that the ſaid Captain was departed with his Company to remote parts of the Countrey: at which the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> grew very angry with the ſaid Captain and Informant, for making him obnoxious both to Tories and Souldiers; and that by their means each party was become his profeſſed enemies: but the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant perſwaded him to have a little patience, for there was a Captain and his Company newly arrived from <hi>England,</hi> to whom the Informant would make his application for aſſiſtance, to the end the fore-mentioned deſign might be accompliſhed: for the Deponent told the ſaid <hi>Cormucke,</hi> that there could be no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of any correſpondency and friendſhip between the ſaid Company and Tories, by reaſon of their late arrival in the Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97682:9"/>
               <head>XXIV.</head>
               <p>That the next night the Informant repaired to <hi>Dundalk</hi> to ſpeak with the ſaid Captain, where he found him accompanied with ſeveral, who continued moſt part of the night drinking Wine and other Liquors; ſo that the Informant deſpaired of a convenient opportunity to deliver his buſineſs, therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated the matter to one of the Souldiers, whom he willed to acquaint his Captain the next morning therewith, and not to divulge the ſame to any, which he promiſed to do; and for his encouragement the Informant gave him a piece of money; but the ſaid Souldier forgot his promiſe, and declared the buſineſs to one of his drunken companions, who willed the Informant to get up early in the morning, and to accompany him to his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains Chamber, who he was ſure would be glad of the news; further he confirmed the matter, by making Proclamation in the audience of all the Company that was near, that he would not depart with the Deponent, till the ſaid Rebel <hi>Hanlon</hi> was betrayed, and himſelf performed what he had promiſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <p>That the Informant went to the ſaid Captain (by name <hi>Coult</hi>) and made him ſenſible of all, and how Captain <hi>Butler</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted when the buſineſs was brought near a period; alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of one of the Souldiers, whom he had employed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his Captain, and inſtead thereof, had fooliſhly publiſhed the ſame; for which the ſaid Captain blamed the Informant for truſting any but himſelf: but withal, deſired him to uſe his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, and he ſhould have aſſiſtance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <head>XXVI.</head>
               <p>That through the rumour that ſpread through the ſaid Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers report, all or moſt people were poſſeſs'd, that the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant received a large ſumm of money from the ſaid Captain <hi>Coult,</hi> to bring in the heads of ſeveral of the chief Tories and Rebels, among others one <hi>Neale,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Cormucke,</hi> both Tories; all which was ſpread abroad by the means of lying fame. All the ſaid Tories verily believed the report except <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mucke,</hi> who well knew the Informants deſign; but the reſt made ſolemn vows to kill the Informant in the firſt place they met him; the Informant getting intelligence hereof, betook himſelf to a habitation at <hi>Dundalk,</hi> where he continued a certain ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97682:9"/>
but one day going thence to viſit his Pariſh, accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with on y one Fryer <hi>Duffee,</hi> as they paſſed by the Hill of <hi>Carriſtickin</hi> they were eſpied by the foreſaid Tories, among whom was the ſaid <hi>Cormucke;</hi> and coming violently all together upon the Informant, he was thereat ſurprized; but <hi>Cormucke</hi> immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly interpoſed between the Informant and them, making oath that whoſoever ſhould lay hands on the ſaid Informant ſhould in the like manner periſh; and <hi>Cormucke</hi> demanding what might be his crime, they told him he was a Rogue, and had contracted with Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Coult</hi> for a ſumm of money to bring in their Heads, but the Informant proteſted the contrary; and that he never men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned their names to the ſaid Captain; (which indeed was true, for his only aim was to ſurprize <hi>Hanlon</hi>) whereupon they were ſatisfied: and the Deponent admitted to reſort to his Pariſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <head>XXVII.</head>
               <p>That the ſaid <hi>Redmond</hi> departed at this rumour to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Conaught,</hi> where he exerciſed his Diabolical Function for a time: ſo that the Informant ſent word to the ſaid Captain <hi>Coult</hi> that he was departed <hi>Ulſter,</hi> and that nothing could be executed againſt him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>XXVIII.</head>
               <p>That within two months following Captain <hi>Butler</hi> and his Company returned, and Captain <hi>Coult</hi> departed from <hi>Dundalk;</hi> upon which the Informant gave notice to the ſaid <hi>Cormucke,</hi> telling him that now Captain <hi>Butler</hi> was returned; and that if he did not perform what he had promiſed touching <hi>Hanlon,</hi> the Informant ſhould prove his greateſt enemy: unto which the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> promiſed to be very diligent therein at the ſaid <hi>Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi>'s return, but that at preſent he was abſent our of the Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>XXIX.</head>
               <p>That the ſaid <hi>Cormucke,</hi> the better to bring his buſineſs to perfection, committed the ſecret to one <hi>Neale,</hi> who he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected would be partaker with him in the ſaid ſervice; the which the ſaid <hi>Neale</hi> faithfully promiſed to do, and in order thereunto went to the ſaid <hi>Redmond,</hi> to learn what time he would return, where <hi>Cormucke</hi> expected him.</p>
               <p>But the ſaid <hi>Neale</hi> remaining ſix days with the ſaid <hi>Hanlon,</hi> in that time he diſcovered to him the deſign of <hi>Cormucke,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97682:10"/>
which <hi>Hanlon</hi> hearing, bound <hi>Neale</hi> by Oath not to let <hi>Cormucke</hi> know that he had ſhewed him the matter, but diſſemble the ſame; and that in the interim he would ſend one of his men to wait an opportunity to kill the ſaid <hi>Cormucke;</hi> and withal, that he would give <hi>Neale</hi> ten pounds; with which reſolution the ſaid <hi>Neale</hi> and one <hi>Mackardle</hi> departed to <hi>Cormucke,</hi> to whom they coloured the buſineſs with much deceit, vilifying the ſaid <hi>Redmond</hi> very much, and ſaying that he divided the ſpoil un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally among his men, and for their own parts they did not approve of ſuch ſhuffling; and that they intended to deſert him, and keep company with their equals, and not to be inſulted over any longer by him: all this they ſaid to delude the ſaid <hi>Cormucke,</hi> and to ingratiate themſelves into his favour; adding, that it was an eaſie matter to ſurprize <hi>Redmond,</hi> for (ſaid <hi>Neale</hi>) himſelf and his Wife lye moſt nights without a guard.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <head>XXX.</head>
               <p>That the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> willing to haſten his enterprize, willed the ſaid <hi>Neale</hi> to accompany him to the houſe of Enſign <hi>John Smith,</hi> there to get ſome powder, the better to furniſh himſelf, as he was accuſtomed to do; ſaying he had ſome buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with Mr. <hi>John Dermond:</hi> whither they came, it being half a mile diſtant from the ſaid Enſign <hi>John Smith</hi>'s houſe; where they had not been long drinking, but the ſaid <hi>Neale,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a quarrel, fell to abuſe the ſaid <hi>Dermond</hi> in his own houſe, for which the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> reproved him; at length came thither <hi>Cormucke</hi>'s two brothers, the one ſervant to Lieutenant <hi>Baker,</hi> the other ſervant to Enſign <hi>John Smith;</hi> they came to the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> to re-mind him of his Father that was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a little before, and that the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> ſhould intercede with the ſaid Enſign <hi>John Smith</hi> for his releaſement, and that the ſaid Enſign would write with one of them thereabout; both which Brothers of <hi>Cormucke</hi> accompanied him out of the houſe, the rather becauſe he reproved the ſaid <hi>Neale</hi> for his abuſe to the ſaid <hi>Dermond,</hi> and leſt a difference ſhould ariſe therefore, hard words having already paſſed; the ſaid <hi>Cormucke</hi> having before over-charged one of his Piſtols, left it with the ſaid <hi>Neale</hi> before they parted the houſe, and went to Enſign <hi>John Smith</hi>'s houſe; the two Brethren of <hi>Cormucke</hi> going ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance before: when the ſaid <hi>Neale</hi> came to the Enſigns houſe, he knocked at the door ſomewhat too hard, for which <hi>Cormucke</hi> was ſomewhat angry with <hi>Neale;</hi> which he perceiving took the ſaid Piſtol, with which he ſhot <hi>Cormucke;</hi> asking him whether he had the ſame deſign againſt him as he had againſt <hi>Hanlon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97682:10"/>with that <hi>Cormuck</hi> fell off his Horſe mortally wounded,<note place="margin">It may be ſuppoſed the ſaid <hi>Neal</hi> made haſte to <hi>Redmond</hi> for his reward, for now he had merited Twenty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Ten pounds; but conſider it was the price of Blood.</note> and the ſaid <hi>Neal</hi> put ſpurs to his, and fled, with only the Stock in his hand, the Piſtol breaking by reaſon of the Charge; at the cry of the ſaid <hi>Cormuck,</hi> his brethren haſted back, and the Enſign alſo waked, it being the night-time, and came to ſee the ſaid <hi>Cormuck</hi> who lay wallowing in his Blood, and his Brethren with others carried him near to another Brothers Houſe, half a mile diſtant; in the mean time a Servant of Lieutenant <hi>Bakers</hi> came poſting in all haſt to the Informants Houſe, pretending to the Informant, that his Wife lay at the point of death and that he feared ſhe would not live his coming, except he haſted; the Informant made not the leaſt delay, but got up, and immediately followed the Meſſenger, till he had brought him where the ſaid <hi>Cormuck</hi> was, in a deplorable condition, but his Life not quite expired; many of his Kindred and acquaintance being preſent, the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent examined him of the matter, and in his reply, he ſaid, that <hi>Neale</hi> had betrayed him; withall part of the Stock of the ſaid Piſtol was there produced which had wounded him, and that near Enſign <hi>John Smith</hi>'s Houſe; but the Informant enquired of him, whether any belonging to the ſaid Enſign had a hand therein? but he anſwered in the Negative. Sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly after this, there was ſent a Meſſenger from Enſign <hi>John Smith</hi> to ſee the ſaid <hi>Cormuck,</hi> and to know if he want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any thing; but at that time was nothing more wanting, than ſomething to prolong Life, which could not be procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and therefore in a ſhort time he gave up the Ghoſt. The Deponent having departed, there came a Brother of the ſaid <hi>Cormuck,</hi> accompanied with Lieutenant <hi>Baker</hi> to ſee him, but ere they came he was dead; after the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi>'s depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Informant came to the place where the ſaid <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muck</hi>'s Body was, and there found one <hi>Patrick Kernan,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly a Servant to the ſaid <hi>Baker,</hi> who was wont to ſell the Tories ſtolen Horſes in remote parts of the Countrey, now was there imployed to make a Bier for the Corps of the ſaid <hi>Cormuck;</hi> this <hi>Patrick</hi> was married to the Siſter-in-law of the ſaid <hi>Neal</hi> that had killed <hi>Cormuck:</hi> now the Brethren of the ſaid <hi>Cormuck</hi> conſulted with the Informant what to do with the Corps, and he adviſed them to have it carried by the aſſiſtance of ſome, to a place appointed for his buryal, and that one of the Brothers, <hi>viz. Hugh Murphy</hi> ſhould go to the ſaid <hi>Neal</hi> and his confederates, feignedly to inform, that the death of <hi>Cormuck</hi> was not imputed to <hi>Neal,</hi> but that it appeared to be accidental, to the end the ſaid <hi>Neal</hi> might
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97682:11"/>
come to the Burying, and thereby be ſurprized by the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Cormuck;</hi> and that if <hi>Neal</hi> complied with him, the Informant to have notice thereof, and that he would ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly come to the place accidentally, to the end he might be inſtrumentally ſervicable to detain the ſaid Tories by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying them to drink, till ſuch time as the Guard might be ſent for to <hi>Dundalk</hi> in that Interim, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <head>XXXI.</head>
               <p>That when this Stratagem was laid, it was concluded that the ſaid <hi>Cormuck</hi> ſhould not be removed until the ſaid <hi>Hugh,</hi> Brother of <hi>Cormuck,</hi> ſhould find <hi>Neal,</hi> which he at length did, and by many proteſtations and feigned words, prevail'd with him to come to <hi>Cormuck</hi>'s Burial, of which, the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant had notice to meet them near the Church; and to avoid ſuſpition, he took his Horſe and carried his Siſter behind him, and tarried a while in the ſaid place ere the Burying came, at laſt he ſaw the Company that attended the Corps coming, and amongſt the reſt the ſaid <hi>Neal,</hi> and another Tory, by name <hi>Macklevy,</hi> which the Brethren of the deceaſed invited to the Ale-houſe after the Burial was over, which the ſaid <hi>Neal</hi> and company embraced, the Deponent going before to the next publick Houſe, and giving order if any came to enquire for him, that they ſhould not want what Liquor they deſired and he would pay all; having giving this order, the Informant went into the company of ſome Gentlemen then in the Houſe; the Brethren of the ſaid <hi>Cormuck</hi> draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near the Houſe with the ſaid <hi>Neal,</hi> it was obſerved by <hi>Neal</hi> and his Company that there were Strangers drinking, ſo refuſed to go in, but drank in the Backſide; but one <hi>Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan</hi> aforementioned (who made the Bier for <hi>Cormuck</hi>'s Corps) deſired the ſaid <hi>Neal</hi> to depart, being his Kinſman and Goſſip, for that he ſuſpected the ſaid <hi>Cormuck</hi>'s Brethren hatch'd ſome miſchief againſt him; by which means he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came cautious of himſelf, and told the Company he would ſtay no longer, ſome of which inform'd the Deponent thereof, therefore he went himſelf to perſwade them to ſtay, which they refuſed, alledging it dangerous for them to be ſo publick, and therewith departed; the which the Informant obſerving, gave the ſaid <hi>Hugh</hi> a piece of Money to have them to another place more remote, and there detain them with Drink, till the Deponent might find out ſome means to ſurprize them, which he would be as ſpeedy in as he could;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97682:11"/>
but <hi>Hugh,</hi> nor the reſt, could not prevail to make them ſtay at any place, by reaſon of the ſaid <hi>Kernan</hi> who kept them company, giving them ſtill caution to be careful of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. As the ſaid <hi>Hugh,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Cormuck</hi>'s Brethren departed with <hi>Neal</hi> and his Company, <hi>Neal</hi> kiſſed a Siſter of theirs; but when he was gone a good diſtance, one of the Brothers was ſo angry, that he ſtruck her for having ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with her Brothers murderer; at which ſhe cried out, and <hi>Neal</hi> hearing, return'd back, and would have killed the ſaid Brother, had not a Kinſman of <hi>Cormuck</hi> ſtept in between and thrown <hi>Neal</hi> down, and had certainly kill'd him, had not <hi>Kernan</hi> prevented, by taking him by the Hair of the Head from off the ſaid <hi>Torey;</hi> being in this confuſion, there was great noiſe, which the Informant hearing, did haſtily, ride to underſtand the matter, and ſeeing the buſtle that the ſaid <hi>Cormuck</hi>'s Brethren made in ſo inconvenient a place, was vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they ſhould diſcover themſelves and intentions to the ſaid Tories, being there was no probability of effecting their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize in the open Fields: He therefore colour'd the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and perſwaded the Tories, that no evil deſign was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended againſt them; but <hi>Kernan</hi> replyed, they would be murthered if they haſtened not away, which counſel of his they took, and departed with him: But the Informant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeched the ſaid Brethren not to let their Brothers death (the ſaid <hi>Cormuck</hi>) go unrevenged, which they promiſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <head>XXXII.</head>
               <p>That a report was ſpread abroad, that <hi>Cormuck</hi> was ſlain near Enſign <hi>John Smiths,</hi> that he alſo was acceſſary to his death; which he in great fury ſware to ſome perſons, that he, nor any of his Family had a hand therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <head>XXXIII.</head>
               <p>That a difference happening between Mr. <hi>John Dermond,</hi> and Enſign <hi>John Smith, Dermond</hi> upbraiding him with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauding the King of Exciſe, and of furniſhing the Tories with Ammunition; the ſaid Enſign alledging the ſaid <hi>Dermond</hi> to be confederate with the Tories when <hi>Cormuck</hi> was killed, for to plunder the ſaid Enſign's Houſe, had not <hi>Cormuck</hi>'s death prevented their deſign. The Enſign doubting what this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference might produce, and fearing ſome of the perſons privy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97682:12"/>
to his and Lientenant <hi>Bakers,</hi> fails in relieving the Tories, ſends for one of them that was more than ordinary acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therewith, by name <hi>William Murphy,</hi> then Servant to Lieutenant <hi>Baker,</hi> and under pretence of having him to ride before his Daughter to <hi>Dundalk,</hi> ſent him with a Note to the Bayly to have him Impriſoned, which when the Bayly ſaw, did according to the order given him therein from <hi>Smith.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>XXXIV.</head>
               <p>That Two Brethren of <hi>Cormucks,</hi> who the Deponent wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to revenge their Brothers Blood upon the Tories, one day eſpied <hi>Hanlon,</hi> and came to the Informant, and made him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted therewith, complaining, they were uncapable of proſecuting the matter, by reaſon they feared their Maſter, the ſaid Enſign, who pretended they ſought after his Life, and therefore ſearch was made after them, in order to their Impriſonment; and that the Enſign might have no juſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, deſired the Informant to ſatisfie him with the truth, that no ſuch thing was thought on; wherefore the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant repaired thither, and enquired what might be the cauſe of the Enſign's ſuſpition of the foreſaid matter, ſeeing <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muck</hi>'s dying words rendered him innocent of his Blood, and that his Brethren never thought nor ſpoke thereof? the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign's Wife replied, that her Husband might have killed <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muck</hi> at his pleaſure ſince he became a Tory, but would not moleſt him, and that it was <hi>Kernan</hi> ſuggeſted her Husband that <hi>Cormuck</hi>'s Brothers had a deſign to do him a miſchief; but the Informant replied, that <hi>Kernan</hi> and the Murderer of <hi>Cormuck</hi> ſhould experimentally feel the reward of ſo treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a fact, for he expected ſome good ſervice ſhould ſhortly be performed by Captain <hi>Butler,</hi> at his return to that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <head>XXXV.</head>
               <p>That the Deponent went to the ſaid Spies <hi>(viz.) Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muck</hi>'s brethren, and told them he had ſatisfied the Enſign <hi>Smith</hi>'s Wife concerning them, and therefore deſired them to be active in their buſineſs, in ſpying out <hi>Redmond,</hi> and others of his Companions; the next night following the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent was ſent for to Chriſten a Child to one of the ſaid Enſign <hi>Smith</hi>'s Tenants, who was a near Kinſman to the ſaid
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97682:12"/>
                  <hi>Cormuck</hi> lately Murdered by <hi>Neal,</hi> before the Informant was approached the ſaid Houſe, came a party of the Militia and took one of <hi>Cormuk</hi>'s brethren, and one <hi>Gurtain,</hi> formerly a Footman to him (the ſaid <hi>Cormuck</hi>); the Deponent no ſooner lighted off his Horſe, being come to the ſaid Houſe, but the Deponent was apprehended by the Soldiers, and taken into their Cuſtody, where he had not been but till the next morning, ere he deſired leave from the Soldiers to go to <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and there ſtay in a certain Inn till they came to the ſaid Town; which requeſt was granted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <head>XXXVI.</head>
               <p>That the Informant remained in the place appointed till about Noon, expecting the ſaid Enſign <hi>Smith,</hi> who at length came, and was met with by the Informant at the Bayliffs, who required the Informant to put in Bail, for he was to give in teſtimony on the Kings behalf of ſeveral matters; the Informant replied, that the Enſign was moſt fit to be Bail in that caſe, ſeeing he had brought him thither; but <hi>Smith</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, had he been taken by another, he ſhould not in the leaſt deny the Informant ſo ſmall a kindneſs. After this, the ſaid Informant Enquired of the Bayly what might be the cauſe of his being taken? To which he replied, That it was for being with the ſaid <hi>Cormuck</hi> at his death. Upon which anſwer, the Deponent told the Bayliff of the whole deſign, and that Captain <hi>Butler</hi> was concerned to have it effected by the means of <hi>Cormuck</hi> who was treacherouſly ſlain; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he gave Bail, departed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <head>XXXVII.</head>
               <p>That in purſuit of the forementioned deſign, the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant employed Two more to have <hi>Hanlon</hi> the great Rebel, and <hi>Neal</hi> that kill'd <hi>Cormuck,</hi> trepan'd, and having ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence that <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker</hi> deſigned to ſet at liberty thoſe that before they had Impriſoned,<note place="margin">Note what brave Officers here are, that can be High-way men, and pretend to be ſome of the Kings beſt Subjects at one and the ſame time.</note> which perſons the Informant knew to be Meſſengers between the Tories and the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker,</hi> being by them employed to carry Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Ammunition to ſupply the Tories, and divide the ſpoil that at ſundry times was Robbed from the Countrey by the Tories; therefore the Informant acquainted the ſaid Captain <hi>Butler</hi> therewith, and further told him, that the ſaid perſons might be ſerviceable for Evidence angainſt <hi>Smith</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97682:13"/>
                  <hi>Baker</hi> if they were looked after, ſeeing they were guilty of Receiving and partaking of the Tories Robberies, and furniſhing them as aforeſaid; and alſo Captain <hi>Cox</hi> being then newly made Bayliff, the Informant deſired him not to take Bail for the ſaid Priſoners, to the end they might be more uſeful to diſcover the ſaid confederacy; and alſo the Informant told the Captain, that he had employed two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, with one of <hi>Cormuck</hi>'s brethren, to find out the Tories, which he hoped would anſwer his end in a little time; and the Captain anſwered, he would be ſure to be at home the Week following to give him his aſſiſtance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <head>XXXVIII.</head>
               <p>That the Informant acquainted Captain <hi>Cox</hi> with the ſame matter that he had Captain <hi>Butler,</hi> deſiring him to detain the ſaid Priſoners, leſt upon their enlargement, <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker</hi> might oblige them to be ſilent in what the Informant expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they would declare, which he was ſure they were privy to; the which the Captain promiſed to do, and alſo to be ſecret therein till it might more fully appear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <head>XXXIX.</head>
               <p>That Enſign <hi>Smith</hi> determining to have the Priſoners re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed, found himſelf prevented, and was told they were not to be ſet at liberty till Sir <hi>Hans Hamilton</hi> came to Town; and the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> alſo learnt this was done by the Informants means, at which the ſaid Enſign was enraged, conſidering his own Life, and Son-in-law Lieutenant <hi>Baker,</hi> might be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered by the teſtimony of the foreſaid perſons in Priſon, if they ſhould diſcover; and that it ſeemed the more dubious, by reaſon the releaſment of the ſaid Witneſſes muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Informants advice; thereupon the ſaid Enſign <hi>Smith</hi> made grievous complaints unto ſeveral Gentlemen, that his Houſe was in agitation to be burnt, and himſelf and Family deſtroyed by the Tories, under pretence that he had occaſioned the death of <hi>Cormuck,</hi> and that one <hi>Edmond Murphy</hi> a Prieſt, was the Ring-leader of this deſign; and having informed the Deponents Father with thoſe things, the Father of the ſaid Informant ſent for him, demanding the Reaſons, and giving him ſharp rebukes; to which the Informant made anſwer, that he never had given an Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation againſt the ſaid Enſign in his life; of which the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent's
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97682:13"/>
Father ſatisfied the ſaid Enſign <hi>Smith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Reader muſt obſerve that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formant did not promiſe his Father he would not diſcover his villany, by that yet he had not.</note> who ſo far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to the matter, that he diſmiſſed thoſe perſons, who for ſeveral nights before guarded his Houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <head>XL.</head>
               <p>That about the time appointed that Captain <hi>Butler</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to come home, came <hi>Hugh Murphy</hi> (who was em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to ſpy after <hi>Hanlon</hi> and his confederates) to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent, and told him, if Captain <hi>Butler</hi> and his Soldiers were ready, he could direct them to the place where the ſaid <hi>Hanlon</hi> and company were; the Deponent hearing this news, poſted on Horſeback to <hi>Dundalk,</hi> leaving the Spy half a mile diſtant from the Town, and coming to Captain <hi>Cox,</hi> queried if Captain <hi>Butler</hi> was come thither? But the ſaid Captain <hi>Cox</hi> replied, he was not expected till two or three nights after. Then the Deponent related to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain what an opportunity was loſt, for want of the ſaid Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Butler</hi>'s being at home; for he further added, how the Spy the Informant had imployed, brought him intelligence where they were that ſpoiled the Countrey; to which, the ſaid Captain <hi>Cox</hi> anſwered, the Informant might have a Company of Soldiers to go with the Spy to take <hi>Hanlon;</hi> but the Deponent ſaid, the ſaid Spy had been before fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened by Enſign <hi>John Smith,</hi> and was confident the Soldiers would betray him, except he might have conference with the Captain himſelf; and therefore the Spy at the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mants return, ſaid, he had rather ſtay till Captain <hi>Butler</hi> came home, and that in the interim he would, by the means of ſome Stratagem, cauſe the Tories to remain thereabouts, which he did by Stealing their Horſes, and bringing them remote from the place where they were, and left them there: The Deponent's brethren and others finding the ſaid Horſes, brought them to Sir <hi>Hans Hammilton</hi> (not knowing the deſigns) and purſued all ſuch as enquired after them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="part">
               <head>XLI.</head>
               <p>That the Informant, when Sir <hi>Hans Hamilton</hi> and Captain <hi>Butler</hi> came to <hi>Dundalk,</hi> informed Sir <hi>Hans</hi> of the ſeveral tranſactions, and of <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker;</hi> ſo that the ſaid Sir <hi>Hans</hi> deſired Captain <hi>Moore</hi> to draw up the Deponent's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation againſt <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker,</hi> which he accordingly did: but the Deponent deſired their ſecrecy therein till
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97682:14"/>
                  <hi>Hanlon</hi> the great Rebel might be taken, which the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent hoped in a ſhort time to effect; and added, that Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Butler</hi>'s abſence was the cauſe of his eſcape hitherto; but alſo informed them, if they in the leaſt doubted of the truth of his Informations againſt the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker,</hi> he could produce Forty to confirm the ſame, ſo they might come privately; and at that inſtant, one <hi>Phelemy Murphy</hi> paſſing by, was called in, and asked, if ever he ſaw <hi>Smith</hi> or <hi>Baker</hi> in company with the Tories, aſſociating themſelves together in any recreations? and whether he was ſworn to keep ſecrecy of their meeting? And the ſaid <hi>Phelemy</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to this purpoſe (to Sir <hi>Hans</hi>) Dear Sir, do not give occaſion that I may be hanged or murdered, between the Soldiers and the Tories; and moreover I have my Fathers Curſe, if I give an Information againſt <hi>Smith</hi> or <hi>Baker;</hi> but the verity I ſhall declare to your ſelf another time, but not by way of Information. Then replied Sir <hi>Hans,</hi> I perceive the Prieſt ſpeaks the truth, and you ſhall; and you, quoth he to the ſaid <hi>Phelemy</hi> ſhall appear at the Aſſize; but he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the contrary, that he would not; and hereupon Sir <hi>Hans</hi> departed to another Room.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <head>XLII.</head>
               <p>That the Deponent had information by the Wife of the ſaid Spy <hi>(viz.) Hugh Murphy,</hi> that he kept a feigned cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency with the Tories, and that he went in great danger, by reaſon they began to have ſome ſuſpition of him, for that he would not be competitor in their Robberies; whereupon the Deponent went to the Captain, and made him acquainted with all, and the ſaid Captain repaired to Sir <hi>Hans Hamilton</hi> to have his advice therein, which done, came to the Deponent, and ordered him to acquaint the Spy to give them notice of the firſt and moſt convenient oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity in that matter; the Said Spy did dayly ſend the State of the Tories, which the Deponent communicated to Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Butler</hi> in writing by a certain Damſel, to avoid ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <head>XLIII.</head>
               <p>That about the latter end of <hi>October,</hi> 1679. the ſaid Spy came to the Informant, and told him that the Tories would endeavour to get a booty about <hi>Dundalk,</hi> and that himſelf
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97682:14"/>
would come along with them, and that when they went to hide it till the time of diſtribution, he would give the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent cogniſance of the place, that the Company of Soldiers might be placed in Ambuſh hard by, that when the ſaid To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries came to divide the ſpoil, they might be ſurprized.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="part">
               <head>XLIV.</head>
               <p>That about this matter, the Informant repaired to the ſaid Captain <hi>Butler,</hi> and made him acquainted with the opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that ſeemed to offer it ſelf; the ſaid Captain in his anſwer, among other diſcourſes, told the Deponent, that one <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
                  <hi>Hill,</hi> a Privy Councellor, deſigned to Impriſon the Deponent, wherefore the ſaid Deponent deſired the Captain to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him to the ſaid <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
                  <hi>Hill,</hi> to know what he had to alledg againſt him, which the Captain did; coming there, the ſaid Captain gave <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
                  <hi>Hill</hi> to underſtand the Informants buſineſs, which was to know what he had committed worthy of cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. The ſaid <abbr>Eſq</abbr> having called the Informant, required of him by what authority he exerciſed his Prieſtly function? The Deponent replied, by the ſame that all the Prieſts in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom did theirs. But the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> proceeded to examine, whether the Deponent was authorized by <hi>Oliver Pluncket</hi> to ſay Maſs? But the Deponent anſwered, Sir <hi>Hans Hamilton</hi> was able to give a good account of him; and that he thought there was no ſuch neceſſity for ſo ſtrict an examination, ſeeing he was bound over to proſecute ſuch matters as Sir <hi>Hans</hi> was acquainted with, as an Evidence in the Kings behalf. With that, the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> enquired if the Informant knew one <hi>Done<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> or did he <hi>in Verbo Sacerdotis,</hi> receive any Knives from the Tories? The Informant anſwered, he never received any Knives from the Tories in his Life. Lieutenant <hi>Baker</hi> being preſent, told the ſaid <hi>Hill,</hi> that the Informant maintained continual correſpondency with the Tories; to which the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent replied, that he never was ſo familiar with them as to be Goſſip to their Children, nor aſſociated himſelf in their company, as the Lieutenant had done in ſeveral places, and to the knowledg of many perſons that could prove many more facts of that kind againſt him than he was aware of: At the hearing of this reply from the Deponent, the ſaid Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant <hi>Baker</hi> requeſted leave from the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> to take off the Informants Head, rather than he ſhould be admitted to ſpeak any further; which the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> denied him. The Deponent further added, that he offered the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> his ſervice againſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97682:15"/>
the Tories, which he would never accept of; at which <hi>Baker</hi> hereat, ſaid, who ſhould accept ſervice at the hands of an excommunicated perſon, as the Deponent appeared to be? for that himſelf was aſſured he was excommunicated by his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat <hi>(viz.) Pluncket,</hi> and withal appealed to Captain <hi>Boult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to bear witneſs what he ſaid was very true: The Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent being before well ſatisfied with the ſaid <hi>Boulton</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> confederacy with <hi>Pluncket,</hi> to carry on the Plot by means of the Tories, as well as conniving at <hi>Pluncket</hi>'s Provincial Councel for the deſtruction of all the Proteſtants; and the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> delivering a Letter (wherein conſiſted the weal of the Three Kingdoms) to inform the ſaid <hi>Pluncket</hi> and the reſt of the Conſpirators, of the diabolical councel at <hi>Artpatrick,</hi> that therefore the Deponent dared not to take any notice of the ſaid Plot before them, deſired only, that the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> and the reſt would bear him witneſs, that the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> ſaid the Deponent was denounced excommunicated; acquainting them further, if he was cenſured by them worthy of Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, he would relieve himſelf by a <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> to have the matter to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and that there he would manifeſt all their Knavery; but the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> anſwered, he would hinder his <hi>Habeas Corpus.</hi> The Deponent in the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>Thou whited wall, ſhall I not have the priviledg of the Law?</hi> Upon which, <hi>Hill</hi> wrote a Mittimus, that <hi>Edmond Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi> ſhould be ſent to Priſon without Bail or Mainprize. The Deponent not deſparing of hope altogether, that when Sir <hi>Hans Hamilton</hi> came to the Countrey he ſhould have his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement procured; in the interim the Deponent made his application to one Mr. <hi>William Hetherington,</hi> ſhewed him the ſeveral abuſes that was put upon him, for two things; Firſt, his endeavour to ſuppreſs the Tories. Secondly, his making manifeſt that the Kingdom was privately to be invaded by a foraign enemy, through the means of ſeveral Conſpirators. To which relation Mr. <hi>Hetherington</hi> ſcarce gave credit; but for the better confirmation, <hi>James Mackenna,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Plunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket</hi>'s man, came to the Deponent in Priſon, and ſaying in the hearing of Mr. <hi>Hethrington,</hi> how treacherous the Deponent had been in betraying the councel held at <hi>Artpatrick</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; and that he was ſure Primat <hi>Pluncket</hi> would never be concerned to have him releaſed, (the ſaid <hi>Mackenna</hi> not at all doubting that Mr. <hi>Hetherington</hi> took notice of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) but the Deponent told him, if it was to be done again, he ſhould do it the very next day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:97682:15"/>
               <head>XLV.</head>
               <p>That the Spy whom the Deponent had formerly employed to find out the Tories, was now encouraged by Captain <hi>Butler</hi> and Sir <hi>Hans Hamilton</hi> to keep correſpondency with the Tories, and accompany them, till ſuch time he might have an opportunity to betray them all at once; the ſaid To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with the forementioned Spy, having obtained their hearts deſire, by ſurprizing a conſiderable booty near <hi>Dundalk,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in company with Fourteen of the ſaid Rebels, who laid up the prize in a place for that purpoſe till it might be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided at a time appointed; at this time the ſaid Spy conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it a convenient opportunity to have his end accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by placing an ambuſh near where the ſaid booty was hid, and that at the time of diſtributing they might be taken; hereupon the Spy enquired narrowly after the Deponent, and hearing that he was apprehended, ſends his Brothers Wife to acquaint him, that all that formerly he endeavoured to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh, was juſt now brought near to a period, if he the ſaid Spy might be but ſecured, and that nothing might be laid to his charge for accompanying the Tories, ſeeing it was to a good end. Upon this Information, the Informant ſends for Mr. <hi>Hetherington,</hi> to whom he imparted the whole matter, which the ſaid <hi>Hetherington</hi> hearing, promiſed the Spy Ten pounds of his own Money for his good ſervice, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with deſired the Deponent might be careful to let Captain <hi>Butler</hi> and Captain <hi>Cox</hi> be acquainted therewith; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Deponent deſired the ſaid Captain <hi>Butler,</hi> that one of the Witneſſes whom the Doponent named, (who after was caſt into Priſon for a pretended miſdemeanour) might be privately bound over to proſecute the matter, which Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Butler</hi> condeſcended to; but Captain <hi>Cox</hi> would by no means take Bail for him, for that <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker</hi> had order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the contrary, and being overſeers of the ſaid Priſon, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd to have the Witneſſes tranſported without Judg, Jury, Witneſs, or Accuſer: In this Confuſion, the opportunity of apprehending the Tories as aforeſaid, was loſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="part">
               <head>XLVI.</head>
               <p>That Mr. <hi>Hetherington,</hi> by intelligence he received at <hi>Dundalk,</hi> both from the Witneſſes and others, was ſo well ſatisfied in the matter; ſo that he reproved <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:97682:16"/>
of their unjuſt proceedings, as well in reference to the Tories, as to the Letter the Deponent intruſted them with, touching the Provincial Council, mentioned in the Deponent's Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the Plot; withal the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hetherington</hi> deſired the Deponent not to concern himſelf with Sir <hi>Hans Hamilton,</hi> or any other, till ſuch time he might be relieved by a <hi>Habeas Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus;</hi> and himſelf engaged all he was worth upon the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent's juſt and lawful Cauſe; after which, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi> departed to <hi>Dublin</hi> and Impriſoned <hi>Pluncket;</hi> the next day following, the Deponent ſent him many conſiderable Papers touching the Plot, and Money to have himſelf, the ſaid Deponent, relieved by a <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> which things the Informant ſent by the Jaylor's Brother, who delivered nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Money nor Papers to Mr. <hi>Hetherington,</hi> but only the Pope's Bull, which the Meſſenger thought to be ſome Leaſe appertaining to the Deponent, otherwiſe had retained that alſo. The ſaid <hi>Hugh,</hi> the Jaylor's Brother, having betrayed the Deponent, by keeping his Papers and Money, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the matters therein contained to <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker,</hi> who underſtood, that one <hi>Art Murphy</hi> (which the Deponent na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for a Witneſs) had ſomewhat to inform againſt them, got a Mittimus from Captain <hi>Boulton</hi> to have him committed (for ſome pretended miſdemeanour) to Priſon, where he was yoaked and chained, which the Deponent finding fault with, was ſerved the ſame ſauce, whereas he before had his liberty to go abroad with his Keeper, keeping the ſaid Deponent from any ſuſtenance from <hi>Monday</hi> to <hi>Friday,</hi> only a piece of Bread that one of the Priſoners ſtole, the Deponent partook of, this being done by <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker</hi>'s command.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="part">
               <head>XLVII.</head>
               <p>That during this extremity of the Deponent's, my Lord Lieutenant <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> was made acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Capt. <hi>Butler</hi> and Capt. <hi>Cox,</hi> that a certain Prieſt was groſly abuſed, for giving information in the Kings behalf of a Confederacy that was between ſome of the Officers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and the Tories, which the ſaid Prieſt, or Deponent, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to be ſecretly kept till the Tories might be taken; which matter the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> hearing, took it in further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. The Deponent's Friends hearing of his troubles, requeſted the Jaylor that he would take the Priſoner to his own Houſe, for which he ſhould be conſidered, and that the Informant ſhould be perſwaded to give in Bail in a ſhort time,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97682:16"/>
which requeſt of theirs was granted: In the interim all the Petitions that the Informant ſent to the D. of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and other Letters to Mr. <hi>Hetherington</hi> (then in <hi>Dublin</hi>) were ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the Poſt-office, by the means of the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker.</hi> The Deponent having obtained more liberty than before, feared it ſhould coſt him his Life, therefore determined to go to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and leave his Brother ſecurity till he returned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before informed by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hetherington,</hi> in a Letter, that he had taken <hi>Pluncket,</hi> and that a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> would be ready for the Deponent; which he no ſooner underſtood, but went (without taking notice of any perſon) with all the expedition he could for <hi>Dublin,</hi> and at his arrival acquainted ſeveral there how he had eſcaped the hands of violence; and at that inſtant the Informants grievances was carried before the D. of <hi>Ormond</hi> again, who ſent for the Deponent the next day, to whom he related the whole buſineſs of the Officers and Tories; to all which, the ſaid Duke promiſed, that juſtice ſhould be done, and that the Country ſhould be redreſſed, and withal, acknowledged, that he had received the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent's Letter, encloſed in Capt. <hi>Butlers,</hi> touching theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, a year before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="part">
               <head>XLVIII.</head>
               <p>That the Informant, immediately after this conference with the D. of <hi>Ormond,</hi> repaired to Mr. <hi>Hetherington,</hi> and related to him all the paſſages that had paſt between them, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of the Excommunication that was denounced againſt the Informant, that malice was the original cauſe thereof; to which the ſaid <hi>Hetherington</hi> replied, that it was almoſt impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as well as improbable, to have any juſtice done againſt the ſaid <hi>Pluncket,</hi> by reaſon of his ſtrong faction, nor in any other matters relating thereunto; the Informant not taking much notice of the reply, informed the ſaid <hi>Hetherington,</hi> if he would accompany the Deponent to the North, he would produce evidence to prove the whole that before he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, and more alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="part">
               <head>XLIX.</head>
               <p>That many days after, the Informant remained in and about the D. of <hi>Ormond</hi>'s Houſe, attending for a Warrant that he promiſed againſt <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker,</hi> and alſo to bring ſuch Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence as was in Gaol to teſtifie in that behalf; at length an
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97682:17"/>
Order of Reference was granted to Sir <hi>Hans Hamilton,</hi> and a Letter to take Bail for ſuch Evidence as was in Priſon afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, which the Deponent no ſooner received, but acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Mr. <hi>Hetherington,</hi> who went with the Deponent, under the denomination of a Fryer which was lately come from <hi>Rome,</hi> by which means he learned ſeveral matters relating to the Plot and other affairs: the Informant came to Sir <hi>Hans Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miltons,</hi> and brought Bail with him for the Evidence afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; but Sir <hi>Hans</hi> ſaid, he would as well ſummons the reſt that were not Impriſoned; in the mean time the Informant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained he wanted ſafe conduct to proſecute his affairs, to which he alſo anſwered, there was no ſuch neceſſity, ſeeing the D. of <hi>Ormond</hi> did think it needful to ſend ſuch aſſiſtance at firſt: Hereupon the Informant conſulted with Mr. <hi>Hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ington,</hi> and ſo determined to proſecute the deſign.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="part">
               <head>L.</head>
               <p>That the ſaid Lieutenant <hi>Baker,</hi> in the mean time, had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of the Informant's Order of Reference from the Lord Lieutenant, came therefore with ſeveral Armed men to the Deponent's Meeting-place, with a deſign to kill him, but was diſappointed, finding none but the Curat; notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing took the Informant's Brother, and plundered ſeveral of his Friends, and in the night time ſent the Tories to find out the Informant and Mr. <hi>Hetherington,</hi> and ordered they ſhould murther them; but in their purſuit the Deponent and his Friend eſcaped their hands, through the goodneſs of the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they rid on, both of the Soldiers and Tories, who made diligent ſearch after them; hereupon the Deponent and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Hetheringion</hi> ſaw it high time to remove from thoſe parts, and ſtaying for one or two nights within ſome Six miles of the place, in which time came the Wives of the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences in Priſon, with ſeveral of their Friends, and acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Mr. <hi>Hetherington</hi> and the Deponent, both by Letters and word of mouth, that the ſaid Evidences and Priſoners could not ſupport their lives under ſuch miſeries they endured by the means of <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker,</hi> the Gaoler not contenting himſelf to Bolt, Yoak, and Chain them, beating them with an Iron Bar (whereby they had loſt much Blood) and this was to force them to ſign an inſtrument for their tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo that their Evidence might not be given againſt the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker;</hi> hereupon Mr. <hi>Hetherington</hi> repaired to acquaint the D. of <hi>Ormond,</hi> which tranſactions he accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly related, and left it to his conſideration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97682:17"/>
               <head>LI.</head>
               <p>That the Informant alſo haſtening to <hi>Dublin</hi> to bring in more of the matters to my Lord Lieutenant, was drawing up his Examination, when one <hi>Hugh Mac Canna,</hi> who made a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation throughout the City, that the Informant was the cauſe of <hi>Pluncket</hi>'s Impriſonment, the which <hi>Hugh</hi> was ſoon after taken by <hi>George Murphy,</hi> for not delivering the Papers of the Treaſon, when ſent by the Deponent, along with the Bull, to Mr. <hi>Hetherington,</hi> by his hand is ſuppoſed to have delivered it to <hi>Pluncket, Smith</hi> or <hi>Baker;</hi> but he was ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed, alledging the Deponent accuſed none but ſuch as were honeſt men; the Informants being impriſoned gave occaſion to all the Primat's, as well as <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Baker</hi>'s friends, to fill the Town with all manner of ſcandalous and ignominious Characters concerning the Deponent; others came to Priſon, tempting him to Petition for to be tranſported to <hi>France;</hi> underſtanding alſo that Mr. <hi>Hetherington</hi> was concerned in <hi>Pluncket</hi>'s Impriſonment, very diligent enquiry was made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, a general report going up and down the City, that Two Rogues, for their own intereſt, intended to take a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended method to diſcover Treaſon to the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> hoping to have Money for their reward; the one being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the other had eſcaped, and that Five hundred pound ſhould be given to any that took him; and that the next Week there was great hopes he ſhould be proclaimed a Rebel; ſome came to the Deponent alſo, and promiſed him Money and liberty, to declare where the ſaid <hi>Hetherington</hi> was.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="part">
               <head>LII.</head>
               <p>That the Head of the forementioned Spy, that the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant employed to look after the Tories,<note place="margin">This was a notable Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be Chronicled for a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, that could kill a man when he was not able to reſiſt.</note> was brought to the D. of <hi>Ormond,</hi> as a piece of good ſervice done by Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>Baker,</hi> notwithſtanding his being authorized by Sir <hi>Hans Hamilton</hi> and Capt. <hi>Butler</hi> to betray the Tories, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of correſpondency with them, which he was allowed in. The manner of Killing of the ſaid Spy, was when he was at his Houſe ſick in Bed, Lieutenant <hi>Baker</hi> came and knock'd out his Brains with the But-end of a Piſtol or Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, afterwards cut off his Head. That afterwards, the ſaid <hi>Baker</hi> taxed the Countrey for Money for his Head, as if he had been a proclaimed Tory, who never was concerned in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97682:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
any thing, but as one employed to be ſerviceable againſt the Tories; neither was he accounted any other by the Country, nor ever proclaimed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="part">
               <head>LIII.</head>
               <p>That notwithſtanding the Deponent's Petitions, the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Witneſſes were tranſported by the means of Sir <hi>John Davis;</hi> during the Informant's Impriſonment, arrived at <hi>Dublin</hi> from the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> a certain Gentleman, by name <hi>John Curfy,</hi> who was a ſtranger altogether to the Informant, and being demanded the occaſion of his coming to Town, ſaid, he came to confirm the teſtimony of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Prieſt; for this he added, he could confirm what the ſaid Prieſt had ſaid, and relate much more of the like kind. The ſaid perſon being brought under pretence of ſeeing the Deponent, was clapt up in Priſon alſo, under the notion of ſeveral unknown Actions of Debt, and was threatned to be hang'd by my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Booth;</hi> and in that fright gave a Bill of his Hand for what was alledged to his charge, beſides Ten pounds that he paid down, and made proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that he would deny that he had any thing to ſay on the Deponent's behalf; which done, he was diſmiſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
